<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
    
____________________________________________________________________________________________

-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Introduction to add-on development</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Introduction to add-on development">
      <span class="shortdesc">An introduction to Hippo CMS add-on development.</span>

      <p>
        As you are developing the website, you'll need to be able to extend the 
        the Hippo CMS.  Perhaps you have created your own 
        <a href="../../user/information_architects/howto">Document Type</a>, a
        <a href="">[FIXME] site map</a> or some documents with test data.
        It is possible to capture this work in an addon, thereby making
        it possible to use version control, use an automated build process, share
        your work with the <a href="http://forge.hippo-ecm.org/">community</a>,
        etcetera.
      </p>

      <subsection name="Dashboard plugin">
        <p>
          When your project calls for a custom way of representing the content in the
          repository, you have the option of creating your own plugin to achieve this.
          As an example, you can get the dashboard to show a list of the last 5 images
          using the <a href="http://lastimages.forge.hippo-ecm.org/">Last images plugin</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Dashboard plugins are mostly standalone, maybe using some of the services
          as they are made available by the CMS.  See the
          <a href="howto/gui_plugin.html">GUI Plugin</a> page for more information on
          how to create such a plugin.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Custom Perspective">
        <p>
          Maybe the dashboard is too restrictive or you want to reuse some existing
          plugins.  In this case, you have the option of creating your own perspective,
          combining multiple plugins into a coherent view.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Templates">
        <p>
          In a more advanced project, document types get complex and their
          templates need to be customized.  In this case, the CMS itself is not (yet!)
          able to help you out but it is certainly possible to
          <a href="howto/editing_template.html">rearrange the layout</a>
          any way you like.
        </p>

        <p>
          Sometimes, changing layouts is not sufficient and you need the full power of
          an AJAX interface.  Perhaps the template has to update dynamically or
          there are complex constraints on the type.  In this case, it is possible to
          <a href="howto/editing_template_plugin.html">create your own template plugin</a>.
          You can then use the developer-friendly 
          <a href="http://wicket.apache.org/">Wicket</a> component framework to create
          the most advanced user interfaces.
        </p>
      </subsection>

    </section>
  </body>
</document>
