<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2007 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Architecture</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
      <section name="Hippo ECM Architecture">

        <subsection name="Overview">
          <p>
            Hippo ECM consists of a number of seperate components that integrate through
            a standard Java Content Repository interface. This modular architecture is
            based on the notion of seperation of concerns, thereby allowing for maximum
            extensibility, interoperability and scalability.
          </p>
          <p>
            Each component is described in more detail in its own section below.
          </p>
          <img src="../images/architecture-jcr.jpg" alt="Architecture" width="834" height="473"/>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="Hippo Repository">
          <img src="../images/architecture-repo.png" 
            alt="Hippo Repository in the Hippo ECM architecture" width="250" height="473"/>
          <p>
            Hippo Repository is the central component in Hippo ECM. All content is stored
            in the repository, and all content management functionality is implemented
            here. The content and the CMS functionalities are exposed through a standard
            Java Content Repository (JSR-170) interface. Hippo Repository is based on the
            JCR reference implementation, Apache Jackrabbit.
          </p>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="Hippo CMS">
          <img src="../images/architecture-cms.png" 
            alt="Hippo CMS in the Hippo ECM architecture" width="250" height="473"/>
          <p>
            Hippo CMS is a web application, essentially providing the user interface through
            which the content management and administrative functionalities exposed by Hippo
            Repository can be used in an intuitive and user friendly way. Hippo CMS is fully
            customizable through a GUI plugin architecture based on the Apache Wicket web 
            application framework.
          </p>
        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="Hippo Site Toolkit (JSP)">
          <img src="../images/architecture-hstjsp.png" 
            alt="Hippo Site Toolkit (JSP) in the Hippo ECM architecture" width="250" height="473"/>
          <p>
            Hippo Site Toolkit provides the tools for rapid development of websites in a 
            Hippo ECM environment. Features include a templating engine which is easily configurable
            through the Hippo CMS user interface, and a tag library and expression language to
            accomodate the development of a JSP based view layer. 
          </p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="Hippo Portal">
          <img src="../images/architecture-portal.png" 
            alt="Hippo Portal in the Hippo ECM architecture" width="250" height="473"/>
          <p>
            Hippo Portal allows partners, employees and customers to choose their user experience, 
            with personalized applications based on role, context, actions, location, preferences 
            and team collaboration needs. Hippo Portal provides a composite application or business 
            mashup framework and the advanced tooling needed to build flexible, SOA-based solutions, 
            as well as the unmatched scalability required by any size organization.
            Hippo Portal is based on the open source enterprise portal Apache Jetspeed
          </p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="Hippo Site Toolkit (Cocoon)">
          <img src="../images/architecture-hstcocoon.png" 
            alt="Hippo Site Toolkit (Cocoon) in the Hippo ECM architecture" width="250" height="473"/>
          <p>
            A toolkit comparable to the one for JSP is planned for the XML based publishing framework
            Apache Cocoon.
          </p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="Applications">
          <img src="../images/architecture-applications.png" 
            alt="External Applications in the Hippo ECM architecture" width="250" height="473"/>
          <p>
            Through its modular architecture, and its use of the JCR open standard, Hippo ECM
            can integrate with any application, new or existing, as long as it uses the JCR
            API. Examples of applications that can integrate with Hippo ECM are email and
            calendar software, data import and export, wikis, blogs. Details and examples are
            given in the <a href="../delve_into/implement-hippo-ecm/jcr/index.html">JCR Interface</a> section.
          </p>
        </subsection>

      </section>
      

    </body>
</document>
