<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2007 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Components</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Hippo ECM Components">

      <subsection name="Hippo Repository">
        <p>
          Hippo Repository is built on top of <a href="http://jackrabbit.apache.org/"
            title="Apache Jackrabbit">Apache Jackrabbit</a>. Hippo Repository adds extra
          fuctionality to the default Jackrabbit distribution while keeping full compliance with the
          JCR 1.0 <a href="http://jcp.org/aboutJava/communityprocess/review/jsr170/index.html"
            title="JSR 170">JSR 170</a>. The main added features are virtual nodes based on facets (metadata) and
          workflow.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Hippo CMS">
        <p>
          Hippo CMS is a user-friendly content management system for maintaining all your
          information in a structured publication on Internet, intranet or extranet. The key points
          of Hippo CMS are user-friendliness, interoperability and expandability.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Hippo Portal">
        <p>
          Hippo Portal allows partners, employees and customers to choose their user experience,
          with personalized applications based on role, context, actions, location, preferences and
          team collaboration needs. Hippo Portal software provides a composite application or
          business mashup framework and the advanced tooling needed to build flexible, SOA-based
          solutions, as well as the unmatched scalability required by any size organization.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Hippo Sample Applications">
        <p>
          The Hippo Sample Applications are included to demonstrate the possibilities of Hippo ECM.
          They can be used as a base to start development of your own application from. The sample
          applications can also be used out of the box.
        </p>
        <p>
          Sample applications:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Wicket application</li>
          <li>Document importer</li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
