<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Browsing history of a document</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Browsing history of a document">
         <span class='shortdesc'>How to browse the history of a document, i.e. to see the changes to the document over time?</span>

<p>
The CMS can display a preview of the document while browsing.  When a
previewable document is selected in the document listing (middle pane) the CMS
can display the content.  You will see the following:
</p>

<center><img src="../../../../images/versioning-pane.gif" alt="Versioning display screenshot"/></center>

<p>
Initially the current version is show.  With the "Older" link you can browse
back into previous versions of the document, or back again towards the most
current version using the "Newer" link.
</p>

<p>
When browsing like this, the content of the document of previous times is
displayed in the preview area.  Above it, in the gray scaled bar, information
about the version is shown.  The name of the article is shown (which is
constant over all versions, only the current name is shown, renaming or moving
a document is not part of the document history of the document itself but --if
available-- part of the document in which a document is embedded).
</p>

<p>
Furthermore a version number is indicated, which counts from 1, the first
version of a document created towards the most current document, which does
not have a version number yet.  It will show the date and time, when a
historic version of the document was created and until when that version of
the document was the most current document.
</p>

<p>
Note that this is not the same as when the next current document was created,
as it may be that there was no current document in the document history.
</p>

  <subsection name='Alternative'>
   <ul>
     <li><a href='./index.html'>Howto list.</a>.</li>
   </ul>       
  </subsection>


    </section>
    </body>
</document>
