<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author>Hippo</author>
        <title>Components</title>
    </properties>
    <!-- Optional HEAD element, which is copied as is into the XHTML <head> element -->
    <head>
        <meta />
    </head>
    <body>
        <!-- The body of the document contains a number of sections -->
        <section name="Hippo ECM Components">
            
            
            <subsection name="Hippo Repository">
                <p>
                    The Hippo Repository is build on top of <a href="http://jackrabbit.apache.org/" alt="Apache Jackrabbit">Apache Jackrabbit</a>.
                    The Hippo Repository adds extra fuctionality to the default Jackrabbit distribution while keeping full compliance with the 
                    JCR 1.0 <a href="http://jcp.org/aboutJava/communityprocess/review/jsr170/index.html" alt="JSR 170">JSR 170</a>. The main added features 
                    are facets, virtual nodes and workflow.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            
            <subsection name="Hippo CMS">
                <p>
                    Hippo CMS is a user-friendly content management system for maintaining all your 
                    information in a structured publication on Internet, intranet or extranet. The key 
                    points of Hippo CMS are user-friendliness, interoperability and expandability.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            
            <subsection name="Hippo Portal">
                <p>
                    ippo Portal allows partners, employees and customers to chose their user experience, 
                    with personalized applications based on role, context, actions, location, preferences 
                    and team collaboration needs. Hippo Portal software provides a composite application or 
                    business mashup framework and the advanced tooling needed to build flexible, SOA-based 
                    solutions, as well as the unmatched scalability required by any size organization.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            
            <subsection name="Hippo Sample Applications">
                <p>
                    The Hippo Sample Application are included to show the possibilities of Hippo ECM. The sample 
                    applications can be used as an example for and starting of the development of third party 
                    application that want to integrate with Hippo ECM. The sample application can also be used 
                    out of the box.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Sample applications:
                    <ul>
                        <li>Wicket applicaiton</li>
                        <li>Document importer</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>