<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Concepts</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Concepts">

            <p>The initial idea behind the HST 2 is to create a set of components that allow
                developers to create web application with Hippo ECM.
                It's has now grown to a modular set of components that allow the web developer to create a
                web application based on layouts and modules.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Sitemap</li>
                <li>Modules</li>
                <li>Layouts</li>
            </ul>
            
            <subsection name="Sitemap">
                <p>The sitemap is the main controller of the HST2. This is where you can configure your URL space, 
                    attach layouts to a page and attached modules to the containers on your layout.                                        
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Modules">
                <p>A webpage can contain multiple pieces of functionality on one single page. 
                    For instance a homepage that contains a list of news articles, some banners and some text. 
                    Each single element can be split up into a HST2 module. 
                    For a news module, the module will consist of 2 things:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>a template file, for intance a JSP file that renders the news content</li>
                    <li>a contentlocation, which specifies where the news content comes from</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Layouts">
                <p>Each page of a website or web application has it's own layout. 
                    Withing the HST2 configuration you are be able to define the layout that belongs to a certain page. 
                    Each specific layout can contain different placeholders that belong to that page(top, bottom, left, right).</p>
            </subsection>

        </section>

    </body>
</document>
