<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
                          "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
    Copyright 2008 Hippo
    
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
    BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
  -->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>ECM Website Development</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="The &lt;hst:menu&gt; tag">
      <p><b>&lt;hst:menu&gt;</b> tag shows a dynamic menu as read from content in the
        repository.</p>

      <p>Following table shows the attributes of the tag. An attribute's value is first found by the
        directly available value, subsequently by a configuration key if present, then by a default
        value. A configuration key is a key in the configuration file normally called
          <code>hst.properties</code>, as given by a web.xml context parameter (<a
          href="../configuration.html">see here</a>).</p>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Attribute</th>
          <th>Required</th>
          <th>ConfigurationKey</th>
          <th>Default</th>
          <th>Description</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>context</td>
          <td>no</td>
          <td>menutag.context.name</td>
          <td>context</td>
          <td>Optional name by which the tag gets it's context object from request or page
          context.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>location</td>
          <td>no</td>
          <td>menutag.location</td>
          <td>/</td>
          <td>The optional location, relative to the context, pointing to the starting location
            where to search for menu items at level 0.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>level</td>
          <td>no</td>
          <td>-</td>
          <td>0</td>
          <td>The optional level indicating the starting level from which default output is
            generated. </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>depth</td>
          <td>no</td>
          <td>-</td>
          <td>1</td>
          <td>The optional depth indicating, in combination with the level attribute, the end menu
            level for which default output is generated.</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>id</td>
          <td>no</td>
          <td>-</td>
          <td>hst-menu</td>
          <td>The optional id of this menu that reoccurs as id of the outer div tag of the default
            output. Also used as request attribute name for custom output.</td>
        </tr>
      </table>
      <h4>File based configuration</h4>
      <p>Besides the tag attributes, other items can be configured in the configuration file:</p>
      <source><![CDATA[menutag.document.exclude.names
Comma separated list of names of documents that are excluded from the menu. 
Not required, defaults to all documents named 'index'.

menutag.viewfile(.<id>)=
Location of a custom jsp file that is used for outputting the menu, thereby 
overriding the default output. The view file may be specified per instance 
with a postfix that is equal to the tag attribute 'id'.    
Not required, no default.]]></source>

      <h4>Repository based configuration</h4>
      <p>To indicate on the repository side which folders and documents (nodes) are part of the menu
        and which are not, a so-called mixin type can be set on a node. The menu's behaviour is as
        follows:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>On the base level of the repository location indicated by the attribute 'location',
          nodes (typically folders) are included in the menu <b>only if</b> the mixin type
            <b>hst:menuItem</b> is set.</li>
        <li>On deeper levels, <b>all nodes</b> are included.</li>
        <li>Folder subnodes are included <b>except when</b> the mixin type <b>hst:childless</b> is
          set on the repository node.</li>
      </ul>
      <h4>Repository based labelling</h4>
      <p>The menu item labels are created taking the capitalized name of the node.
        If this is not applicable, it may further be specified on a node by the String property
        <b>hst:label</b>.</p>

      <h4>Default HTML output</h4>
      <p>The default menu output is based on a possibly nested, <code>&lt;ul&gt;</code> /
          <code>&lt;li&gt; structure</code>. The id of the outermost
          <code>&lt;ul&gt;</code> tag, useful for CSS styling, is the actual attribute 'id'
        or the default <code>hst-menu</code>.</p>
      <p>The default output will create links for each item, based on reversed URL mapping
        functionality, <a href="../url-mapping.html">see here</a>.</p>

      <h4>Custom HTML output</h4>
      <p>When the configuration item <code>menutag.viewfile</code> is specified, it overrides the
        default output. Instead, a developer can create it's own HTML with a jsp fragment file,
        using standard Java or jsp expression language on an object representing the menu.</p>
      <p>An org.hippoecm.hst.components.Menu object is present in the request under key 'hst-menu',
        which may be overridden by the menu tag attribute 'id'.</p>
      <p>The tag attributes 'level' and 'depth' are present in the request under fixed keys prefixed
        by the id: &lt;id&gt;-level and &lt;id&gt;-depth.</p>
      <p>The MenuItem objects that are retrieved by the 'items' property have the properties
        'label', 'level', 'active', 'path' and 'items'.</p>
      <p>Note that path can easily be converted to an URL by the &lt;hst:encodeURL&gt;
      tag.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
