<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2007-2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>

    <title>Welcome</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Delve into Hippo CMS">

      <!-- [TODO] requires new infographic
        <img src="images/old-infographic.jpg" alt="Clean separation of content storage, management and presentation"/>
              <a href="use-hippo-ecm/index.html"><img alt="use" src="/images/frontpage/use.png" /></a>
        -->

        <p>The Hippo CMS component of the Hippo ECM can manage all content in your company. 
           The userinterface is webbased: content is created and managed via your normal webbrowser, anywhere 
           you have access to your companies intranet. Several users may work on the same document, picture, soundtrack 
           or other piece of content. Rights to change pieces of content or just to read them can be assigned.
           Previous versions of content are stored automatically. Advanced methods to search content are 
           provided.
        </p>

        <p>
          Companies that use Hippo CMS, design their own content structure. Hippo CMS ensures that all content  
          fits into this single structure. Thus, the content base of the company will be filled with information 
          actually useful to the company; required information will actually be there 
          and the content base will be easily understandable and searchable, thanks to its uniformity.    
        </p>

        <table style='td { border:solid;}'>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="quickstart.html"><img class='leftflow' src="../images/frontpage/quickstart.png" />

                <h3>CMS Quickstart Guide</h3></a>

               <p>You can try out Hippo CMS with example content having predefined structure, to see possible features `in action',
                  before designing your own content structure. 
                  To install Hippo CMS with example content, download a quickstart Hippo CMS package. After you studied
                  the example content, your system adminstrator can configure the package for actual use in your company. 
               </p>
            </td>
            <td>
              <a href="use-hippo-ecm/index.html"><img width='50' alt="use" src="../images/frontpage/use.png" />

               <h3>Hippo CMS User Guide</h3></a>

                If you are a (new) user to Hippo CMS and the Hippo CMS is already installed on your system,  
                read the User Guide for a tour through Hippo CMS and to learn Hippo CMS concepts.

            </td>
            <td>
              <a href="run-hippo-ecm/index.html"><img alt="run" src="../images/frontpage/run.png" /></a>

               <h3>CMS System administration Guide</h3>
           
               <p>
                Here, all system administration information for Hippo CMS can found, i.e. installation and configuration.
                The description of installation includes details not
                in the quickstart guide. Configuration of Hippo CMS is often as simple as 
                adding the path to your companies data base server. Without this path, Hippo CMS will use
                a folder on your filesystem to store the content.
	       </p>
               <p>
                If a quickstart package was installed, configuration for actual use requires two
                settings that ensure that the example content is not used and not recreated on your data base server.
	       </p>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="implement-hippo-ecm/index.html"><img alt="implement" src="../images/frontpage/implement.png" /></a>

               <h3>CMS implementation guide</h3>

               <p>
                The Hippo ECM can be tailored to your needs, augmented with your own website-design, 
                and integrated with your other applications to create your own Hippo ECM implementation. 
               </p>
               <p>
                This guides describes the CMS related aspects of the Hippo ECM implementation.
	       </p>
            </td>
            <td>
              <a href="extend-hippo-ecm/index.html"><img alt="extend" src="../images/frontpage/extend.png" /></a>

               <h3>CMS Extension Guide</h3>

                 This guide is for developers of custom plugins for Hippo CMS. Examples are plugins for extra properties
                 of content nodes and plugins for custom userinterfaces for the Hippo CMS.
            </td>
            <td>
              <a href="building/index.html"><img alt="build" src="../images/frontpage/build.png" /></a>

               <h3>CMS Developers Guide</h3>

                 This guide is for Hippo CMS developers, who develop the CMS core engines and the CMS core plugins and
                 the CMS standard package, containing the CMS core engines and a selection of the CMS core plugins.

            </td>
            <!--<li>
              <p>
                <b>Develop Hippo ECM</b>
              </p>
              <p>
                Information for Hippo ECM core developers.
              </p>
            </li>-->
          </tr>
        </table>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
