<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2007 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Frontend Skin Customization</title>
  </properties>
  <head>
  </head>
  <body>
    <section name="Frontend skin customization">

      <p>
        The layout on the screen, the colors and formatting used, and things like the
        icons in place for the front-end are generally known as a skin.  Customizing
        the application to give a different look is performed by applying a different
        skin.  A different skin should <em>not</em> be used to create a different
        functional application.  Functionality is added by incorporating another
        plugin in the packaged product.  This in itself should not lead to having to
        apply a different skin.
      </p>

      <p>
        The most obvious part of a skin is the cascading style sheet (CSS) file.  The
        CSS file determines the default font sizes, spacing, etcetera to be used for
        all elements.  Also part of the skin are icons in use by either CSS file (such
        as declaring a button or background image) or elsewhere.
      </p>

      <p>
        There always needs to be a skin with the CSS file and icons to be used,  a
        packaging project like the CMS needs to supply it. The default
        CMS skin is supplied in the project <code>hippo-ecm-cms-skin</code>. A skin
        itself is an add-on like others and can be combined with other skin plugins.
      </p>

    <subsection name="Create your own skin">

      <p>
        You can create your own skin by creating a project with the same structure and
        content as the hippo-ecm-cms-skin project as supplied in
        <code>cms/skin</code>.  You can also take the hippo-ecm-cms-skin WAR,
        rename it and modify it to your needs.  This works because this add-on is just
        a collection of files, and building the WAR is just a packaging of the files.
        No actual compilation of sources is required.
      </p>

      <p>
        The first thing to do when creating a copy of the skin project is to change
        the name of the artifact in the <code>pom.xml</code> (when building using
        Maven) and in the <code>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/web.xml</code> (or
        WEB-INF/web.xml when modifying the resulting WAR).  Do <em>not</em> use the
        same package name as the default.  The resulting WAR should have a
        different name and different description in the WEB-INF/web.xml.
      </p>

      <p>
        You can <em>not</em> change the context-root of the skin.  All skin files in
        the final produced end-application are retrievale under the <code>skin/</code>
        path.
      </p>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="What to customize">

      <p>
        <dl>
          <dt>Cascading style sheets</dt>
          <dd>
            When creating your own skin you can modify the cascading style sheet in use,
            such as the <code>src/main/webapp/style.css</code>.  In the packaged WAR this
            file is placed in the root of the WAR.  The <code>style.css</code> is the
            primary style file in use, but there are others for specific screens, such as
            the login screen.
          </dd>
    
          <dt>Icons</dt>
          <dd>
            Icons in use are placed in the <code>images</code> directory.  Just put any
            different icons in your own project when you want them different.
          </dd>
    
          <dt>Alternate HTML files</dt>
          <dd>
            Web pages as served back to a browsing client are not single HTML files in the
            front-end.  Rather than single files bound to a specific page requested, a web
            page is composed of HTML fragments.<br/>

            Each item on a web-page is supplied by a piece of program code in the
            front-end.  Together with this Java program code, a HTML fragment in given.
            These HTML fragments are merged into a single HTML file.  These HTML fragment
            files are not defined on a per-page basis, but on the class of the item used.
            Therefore a change to the HTML file representing, for instance a kind of
            button, is reflected in all buttons of that kind used everywhere.<br/>

            By being able to override the HTML for all items, you are able to further customize
            the layout of the pages.
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </p>

      <p>
        To override HTML files, you need to identify which HTML fragment file you need
        to override.  This depends on the add-on you are using and which frontend plugin
        delivers that particular HTML fragment.
      </p>

      <p>
        Suppose an add-on in use defines an item which is a BreadCrumbPlugin.  Next to the
        Java class implementing this item, there is an HTML fragment file:
      </p>

<source>
`-- src
    `-- main
        `-- java
            `-- org
                `-- hippoecm
                    `-- frontend
                        `-- plugins
                            `-- admin
                                `-- breadcrumb
                                    |-- BreadCrumbPlugin.java
                                    `-- BreadCrumbPlugin.html
</source>

      <p>
        This is in the original add-on that supplies the item on the web-page.  If you
        want to provide an override for this HTML fragment in your skin, then put this
        alternate BreadCrumbPlugin.html file in your skin project.
      </p>

      <p>
        Within the skin project, the location of this HTML fragment should be 
        <code>src/main/webapp/org/hippoecm/frontend/plugins/admin/breadcrumb/BreadCrumbPlugin.html</code>
        resulting in the final WAR project as file
        <code>org/hippoecm/frontend/plugins/admin/breadcrumb/BreadCrumbPlugin.html</code>.
      </p>

      <p>
        In summary, the location of an overriding HTML fragment file should follow the
        same directory structure as the original HTML fragment file, but instead of
        the initial location <code>src/main/java</code> you should use
        <code>src/main/webapp</code>.
      </p>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Overview of a skin project">

<source>
|-- pom.xml
`-- src
    `-- main
        `-- site
            ... <i>maven documentation</i>
        `-- webapp
            `-- WEB-INF
                `-- web.xml
            `-- org
                `-- hippoecm
                    `-- frontend
                        ...<i>overriding HTML fragments</i>
</source>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="How to apply a skin">

      <p>
        The end application is a packaging of the core system as well as multiple
        add-ons.  These add-ons are either WAR or JARs which are merged or put
        together in an EAR.
        Please refer to the <a href="../../building/index.html">building
        section</a> on how to compose your end application by adding add-ons to your
        application.
      </p>

      <p>
        The default skin of Hippo CMS 7 is defined by the project that produces the
        hippo-ecm-cms-skin artifact.  If you want to apply a different skin, replace
        this artifact with your own.
      </p>

      <p>
        If you use an EAR target, this means simply replacing the
        <code>hippo-ecm-cms-skin.war</code> by another skin WAR target.  If you use
        a merged WAR target, then you need to rebuild the end WAR with a different
        artifact dependency in the pom.xml.  Replace the dependency to the 
        <code>hippo-ecm-cms-skin</code> artifact by your own skin artifact.
      </p>

    </subsection>

    </section>
  </body>
</document>
