<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Roadmap Hippo CMS</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Roadmap Hippo CMS">
         <span class='shortdesc'>Dates for future releases of Hippo CMS</span> 

            <h3>Release Schedule</h3>
            <p> Hippo works with a monthly development cycle. We believe in the <a
                    href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/cathedral-bazaar/ar01s04.html"
                    >Release Early, Release Often</a> paradigm from the Linux community, and use the
                    <a href="http://www.controlchaos.com/about/">SCRUM development methodology</a>
                to iteratively build our software. </p> We have 4 scheduled <b>releases</b> per
            year. A release is a version for which <a href="http://www.onehippo.com">Hippo</a>
            offers paid support services. See <a href="http://www.onehippo.com/en/support"
                >http://www.onehippo.com/en/support</a> for more information. <p> Here's the Roadmap
                outine for 2009. This is a list of how we intent to roll out functionalities, even though some changes may occur as priorities shift.
           </p>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Scheduled date</th>
                        <th>Release</th>
                        <th>Feature Goals</th>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>December, 2008</td>
                    <td>Hippo CMS v7.0 (r2.02.xx)</td>
                    <td>Folder structure, Template editor, Workflow, Internationalization (i18n),
                        AJAX support, Search, Multi-document tabs, Locking, Authorizations, Plugin
                        architecture, Versioning, Clustering, Scheduled publication, User
                        management, Image and asset galleries</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>March, 2009</td>
                    <td>Hippo CMS v7.1 (r2.05.xx)</td>
                    <td>All standard Hippo CMS 6 features, Faceted browsing, Tagging, Split pane
                        versioning, Migration path CMS 6 to CMS 7, Forms, Metadata extraction (from
                        Word, PDF, etc), Batch workflow actions, HST-2 Configuration editor</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>June, 2009</td>
                    <td>Hippo CMS v7.2 (r2.08.xx)</td>
                    <td>Hippo CMS 6 migration tools, Reporting, Translations workflow</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>September, 2009</td>
                    <td>Hippo CMS v7.3 (r2.11.xx)</td>
                    <td>DMS, BPM, Metadata suggestor, collections, full-repository archiving</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>December, 2009</td>
                    <td>Hippo CMS v7.4 (r2.14.xx)</td>
                    <td>TBD</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            
            <h3>v7.0 (December 2008)</h3>
            <h4>Goal: deliver all basic CMS functionalities, production ready</h4>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Feature</td>
                        <td>Description</td>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Folder structure</td>
                    <td>Information architect creates a free folder structure to contain documents. Every document has one position in the folder tree.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Template editor</td>
                    <td>Developer creates and edits the CMS editing templates using the Template Editor in the CMS.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Workflow</td>
                    <td>Standard Reviewed Actions workflow implemented (author / editor, two step process).</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Internationalization (i18n)</td>
                    <td>All text in the CMS user interface is available in at least two languages: English and Dutch.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>AJAX support</td>
                    <td>Uses AJAX to load parts of the user interface.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Auto-save / document recovery</td>
                    <td>AJAX document editor continuously saves changes in the user's draft version. No loss of data when accidentally navigating away from the CMS.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Search</td>
                    <td>Full-text search as an AJAX dropdown.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Multi-document tabs</td>
                    <td>User can have multiple multiple documents open as tabs.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Locking</td>
                    <td>When someone edits a document, it is locked for others.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Authorizations</td>
                    <td>Restrictions can be set on groups and users, based on properties.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Plugin architecture</td>
                    <td>CMS can be extended by adding plugins, to be downloaded from the Hippo Forge.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Versioning</td>
                    <td>Per publication, a version is stored. Using a dropdown, the user can see the contents of older versions.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Clustering</td>
                    <td>Repository runs in a clustered environment.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Scheduled publication</td>
                    <td>Workflow requests can be set to a time and date.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>User management</td>
                    <td>Users, groups and domains can be edited.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Image and asset galleries</td>
                    <td>Support for galleries that contain images, binary files (PDF, DOC, etc). Thumbnails.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>LDAP support</td>
                    <td>Support for external authorization repositories based on LDAP (Active Directory, OpenLDAP).</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Cross browser support</td>
                    <td>Support for Internet Explorer 6, 7 and Firefox 3</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            
            <h3>v7.1 (March 2009)</h3>
            <h4>Goal: All CMS 6 functionalities + faceted functionalities</h4>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Feature</td>
                        <td>Description</td>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>All standard Hippo CMS 6 features</td>
                    <td>All functionalities that are included in the standard download of Hippo CMS 6 are supported out of the box.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Word import</td>
                    <td></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Faceted browsing</td>
                    <td>Users can create their own views on content, and can navigate and operate the CMS using this interface.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Tagging</td>
                    <td>Tagging support for all documents and gallery items.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Split pane versioning</td>
                    <td>Versions can be viewed side by side</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Migration path CMS 6 to CMS 7</td>
                    <td>Migration path for migrating CMS 6 projects to CMS 7.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Forms</td>
                    <td>Form support. Creating forms from within the CMS, and presentation and validation support from the HST </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Separated deployment</td>
                    <td>The possibility to deploy the CMS and Repository on different machines.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Metadata extraction (from Word, PDF, etc)</td>
                    <td>Automated meta data extraction from assets.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Batch workflow actions</td>
                    <td>Initiate workflow steps on multiple documents at once.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>HST-2 Configuration editor</td>
                    <td>Configuration of the Hippo Site Toolkit from within the CMS.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Content OTAP</td>
                    <td>Automated migration of content sets from Development, to Test, to Acceptance and to Production repositories.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Customer skinning</td>
                    <td>Support customer skinning of CSS and plugins.</td>
                </tr>
            </table>

            <h3>v7.2 (June 2009)</h3>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Feature</td>
                        <td>Description</td>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Metadata / tag suggestors</td>
                    <td>Guiding the user in the metada generation process. Facilitate tagging of large sets of content.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>User profiles</td>
                    <td>Different UI configurations for different user profiles. Casual contributor versus advanced editor.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Hot deployable plugins</td>
                    <td>OSGi support.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Knowledge driven workflow</td>
                    <td>Flexible worfklow configuration based on user profiles and content metadata.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Website templating</td>
                    <td>The possibility to edit Freemarker or JSP templates from within the CMS.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Task management</td>
                    <td>Tasks and workflow items spawning multiple documents, or broader.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>CMIS support</td>
                    <td>REST and CMIS interfaces for developers.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Customizable help</td>
                    <td>Functionality to change the help texts for a specific implementation.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Personalized reporting</td>
                    <td>"My recent documents", "My Tasks", etc</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Advanced Search</td>
                    <td>Searching on metadata, and storing searches as faceted views.</td>
                </tr>
            </table>

        
            <h3>v7.3 (September 2009)</h3>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Feature</td>
                        <td>Description</td>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>DMS functionality</td>
                    <td>Document management capabilities, network share.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>External BPM layer</td>
                    <td>Support for business process management integration.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>OpenOffice integration</td>
                    <td>Native support for OpenOffice documents in the DMS subsystem.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Repository-wide content tagging and labeling</td>
                    <td>Label a "Christmas" edition of your website and schedule it for publication.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Archiver</td>
                    <td>View the contents of the entire repository on a certain date.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Visitor generated metadata management</td>
                    <td>Use visitor behavior and feedback for tagging documents in the repository, in a controlled manner.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Metadata suggestor</td>
                    <td>Suggesting the CMS user what possible metadata could be added to the current document, based on the user's behavior in the CMS itself.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Collections</td>
                    <td>Collections functionality: hand-picked, search or folder selection. Collections can be used for navigation. Collections have workflow.</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
        
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
