<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
 <properties>
  <title>Hippo CMS Contributor Tour</title>
 </properties>
 <body>
  <section name="Hippo CMS Contributor Tour">
    <span class='shortdesc'>To get introduced in the role of CMS Contributor, take the following tour.</span> 

     <p>To get introduced in the role of CMS contributor, you will look over the shoulder of
        Marc, who is a member of the imaginary organization Saraswatia,
        an organization of people very interested in music, art and knowledge. We did not imagine an
        answer to the question whether Saraswatia is a commercial organization, a hobby organization, or both. 
    </p>
    <p>Saraswatia decided to publish an online newspaper about music, art and knowledge. The name will be Sar, which
        is just an abbreviation of `Saraswatia Articles'. 
    </p>
    <p>Marc will add an article about an upcoming multicultural Bazar.
    </p>

   <blockquote>
    <table>
  
     <tr>
      <td>Browser</td>
      <td>
       <span class='web-48 icon-48'/> 
      </td>
      <td>
        Open the Hippo CMS site 
        <a href="http://localhost:8080/cms/">http://localhost:8080/cms/</a> in 
        your browser. 
      </td>
     </tr>
   
     <tr>
      <td>Login</td>
      <td>
       <span class='login-48 icon-48'/> 
      </td>
      <td> 
         <a href="./howto/login.html">Login to Hippo CMS</a> in the CMS account given to you by your 
          CMS administrator. Marc logs in with his name. His password is only known to him, so you do
          not get to see it.
      </td>
     </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>Folder</td>
      <td>
       <span class='user-48 icon-48'/> 
      </td>
      <td> 
         <a href="./howto/folder_tab.html">Goto to the folder</a> to add your document in.
         Marc learned that all articles for Saraswatia's online newspaper are supposed to
         go in the 'sar newspaper' document folder, so he selects that.
      </td>
     </tr>

     <tr>
      <td>Create document</td>
      <td>
       <span class='user-48 icon-48'/> 
      </td>
      <td> 
         <a href="./howto/create_document.html">Create a document</a> to write in.
         For the article about the upcoming multicultural bazaar, Marc creates a
         document named 'multibazar2008'. He selects for it the documenttype 'upcoming',
         because that is the type for upcoming happenings, like the bazaar.
      </td>
     </tr>

     <tr>
      <td>Open document</td>
      <td>
       <span class='user-48 icon-48'/> 
      </td>
      <td> 
         <a href="./howto/goto_document_tab.html">Open the document</a> to start writing.
         Marc opens the document named 'multibazar2008'.
      </td>
     </tr>
 
     <tr>
      <td>fill date</td>
      <td>
       <span class='user-48 icon-48'/> 
      </td>
      <td> 
         <a href="./howto/fill_date_field_in_document.html">Fill a date field</a>.
         Marc sees that he is supposed to fill in on what date the happening, which
         in his case is the bazaar, will be. So he looks up the date and fills it in the document.
      </td>
     </tr>

     <tr>
      <td>fill string</td>
      <td>
       <span class='user-48 icon-48'/> 
      </td>
      <td> 
         <a href="./howto/fill_string_field_in_document.html">Fill a string field</a>.
         Marc sees that he is supposed to type a title for the happening, which
         in his case is the bazaar, and he types 'Multicultural Bazaar 2008' as the title.
      </td>
     </tr>

     <tr>
      <td>fill boolean</td>
      <td>
       <span class='user-48 icon-48'/> 
      </td>
      <td> 
         <a href="./howto/fill_boolean_field_in_document.html">Fill a boolean field</a>.
         Marc sees that he is supposed to answer the question whether the happening is
         indoors. 
         The bazaar is not indoors, so he does not check that checkbox.
         He also is supposed to answer the question whether the happening is
         a recurring happening, i.e. a happening that has occurred before. This is the case,
         so he checks that checkbox.
      </td>
     </tr>

     <tr>
      <td>fill markuped text</td>
      <td>
       <span class='user-48 icon-48'/> 
      </td>
      <td> 
         <a href="./howto/fill_markuped_text_in_document.html">Fill markuped text</a>.
         Marc sees that he can also write a description of the happening and he
         writes an informative text about the upcoming multicultural bazaar.
         He includes the place where the bazaar will be in this description,
         because there is no separate field for it and people need to know.
      </td>
     </tr>

    <tr>
      <td>request publication</td>
      <td>
       <span class='user-48 icon-48'/> 
      </td>
      <td> 
         <a href="./howto/fill_markuped_text_in_document.html">request publication</a>.
         Marc now requests publication of his article. Janine is the editor and she
         will receive this request and accept or reject it.
      </td>
     </tr>

     <tr>
      <td>Logout</td>
      <td>
       <span class='logout-48 icon-48'/> 
      </td>
      <td> 
         <a href="./howto/logout.html">Logout</a>. 
         Marc quits for today.          
      </td>
     </tr>
 
    </table>
   </blockquote>
       
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
