<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2012-2013 Hippo B.V. (http://www.onehippo.com)

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Poll Parameters</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Poll Parameters">
      <p>
        The parameters of the poll plug-in are implemented in the <code>PollProvider</code> delegate class. As long as custom
        components delegate to the PollProvider, they will "inherit" the set of parameters described here.
      </p>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Parameter</th>
          <th>Description</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>poll-docsPath</td>
          <td>
            <p>
              This parameter specifies a repository content path, relative to the site's root node,
              where the poll component should look for active poll documents represented by content beans of class
              <i>poll-docsClass</i>. The path should start with a forward slash ("/"), and should be considered
              mandatory.
            </p>
            <p>
              If multiple matching and active poll documents are found under the specified path, the "first" one will
              be processed.
            </p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>poll-docsClass</td>
          <td>
            This parameter specifies the class of the content beans that contain poll documents
            to be processed by this instantiation of the poll component. By default, the parameter is set to
            <i>org.onehippo.forge.poll.contentbean.PollDocument</i>. If you create your own document type, including
            the poll compound type, you will have to write your own content bean, inheriting from
            <i>org.hippoecm.hst.content.beans.standard.HippoDocumentBean</i>, representing the content of your poll
            documents, and refer to that class through this parameter.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>poll-pollCompoundName</td>
          <td>
            This parameter specifies the JCR name of the poll compound inside your poll
            document. It is used to access the core poll data of your poll document, managed by the PollProvider. By
            default, the parameter is set to <i>poll:poll</i>, which works out of the box for the document type provided
            by the poll plug-in.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>poll-dataPath</td>
          <td>
            This parameter specifies where the poll data (the votes of the poll) are kept. As
            keeping this data together with the poll documents is tricky from a security point of view, the poll
            plug-in, by default, keeps all poll data in a separate root-level folder called <i>/polldata</i> in the
            repository. We recommend to keep this unchanged, as the creation of a root-level repository folder is not
            allowed at runtime.
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
