<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
      <title>Hippo Site Toolkit Roadmap</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
      <section name="Hippo Site Toolkit Development Roadmap">
        <p>This section describes the general development roadmap of the Hippo Site Toolkit for 
           HippoECM. This roadmap is an outline of the functionality and the components that will
           be released in future versions of the HST. <br>
           The development will focus on a flexible and extendible toolkit with which developers
           can create websites with content from HippoECM.
           
           The HST should be a joy to work with when you build a site with the
           repository :-). This roadmap is a general list of components and functionalities that 
           will end up in future releases. Any feedback on these issues is more than welcome</p>
        
        <subsection name="Content to URL Mapping">          
          <p>To display repository content by the view techology (jsp, jsf) a flexible
          mapping is required. Initially this mapping will be configured in a static resource like
          an xml file or by Spring. In a later version this might end up in the repository.
          in a later release </p>
        </subsection>  
        
        <subsection name="Templating">          
          <p>Templating can be very useful in sites that unlock repository content and to
          speed up development. For this purpose the HST will have functionality to add 
          templates of proven templating frameworks to the repository and to maintain them `
          with the cms. The frameworks will include:</p>
           <ul>
            <li>freemarker</li>
            <li>tiles</li>
            <li>velocity</li>
          </ul>
        </subsection> 
        
        <subsection name="Caching">          
          <p>For a good performance the HST will have support for caching.</p>           
        </subsection> 
        
        <subsection name="JSP Tags">          
          <p>The HST will provide a number of useful tags. These can be divided in core tags,
          giving the tools to retrieve and write content to the repository and tags that facility
          more extensive functionality. 
         </p>
          <h4>core tags</h4>
           <ul>
            <li>Tags for retrieving and writing repository content</li>
            <li>A tag for retrieving faceted content</li>
            <li>Support for dictionaries</li>
            <li>A tag that provides context state (the current document, repository connection etc.)</li>
          </ul>
          <h4>other tags</h4>
           <ul>
            <li>A tag for paginated content</li>
            <li>A Poll Tag</li>
            <li>A tag for RSS Feeds</li>
            <li>A tag for follow-ups/comments on documents</li>
            <li></li>
            <li>..and many more</li>
          </ul>
        </subsection> 
      </section>
    </body>
</document>