<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
      <title>Hippo Site Toolkit Roadmap</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
      <section name="Hippo Site Toolkit Development Roadmap">
        <p>This section describes the general development roadmap of the Hippo Site Toolkit for
           HippoECM. This roadmap is an outline of the functionality and the components that will
           be released in future versions of the HST.
           The development will focus on a flexible and extendible toolkit with which developers
           can create websites with content from HippoECM.

           The HST should be a joy to work with when you build a site with the
           repository :-). This roadmap is a general list of components and functionalities that
           will end up in future releases. Any feedback on these issues is more than welcome</p>

        <subsection name="Templating">
          <p>Templating can be very useful in sites that unlock repository content and to
          speed up development. For this purpose the HST will have functionality to add
          templates of proven templating frameworks to the repository and to maintain them
          with the cms. Among the possible templating frameworks are Tiles, Freemarker and Velocity.
          </p>
        </subsection>

        <!--  <subsection name="Caching">
          <p>It is needless to sat that the HST needs to perform properly and this will be kept in mind
          during the development process. To reduce unnecessary template rendering and data transport with the
          repository caching might be a useful technique.
          </p>
        </subsection> -->

        <subsection name="Components">
          <p>A huge focus in the development of the HST is on its component library. One has to
          think of components with basic functionality like retrieving content from and writing data to the repository and of
          higher level components like components for displaying paginated repository content, the generation
          of content as rss feeds, dictionary support, forum functionality, sitemaps and sitemenu's, polls and many more.
          </p>
          <p>Our aim is to create extendible components so that developers can create their own components on top of the available
          component stack and we encourage the contribution of these components to Onehippo's forge.
          </p>
          <p>
          Together with the content modelling features of Hippo ECM this results in a powerful framework to create sites
          that expose repository content in a structural manner with rich component based functionality in an efficient way.
          </p>
           <p>
            The initial chosen technology for the HST is JSP and tag libraries.
          </p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
</document>
