<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Run a development package</title>
  </properties>
  <body>

   <section name="Run a development package">
    <span class='shortdesc'>How to build the package of a project and run it, all on the fly?</span>

        <p>
         In production, the Hippo CMS and any addons are run by <a href="../../sysadmin/installation/in_servlet_container.html">
         deploying the application wars in an application server</a>, but during development you will
         want to have a faster way, testing and improving your application often during your
         development cycle.
        </p>
        <p>
         To facilitate development it is possible to run Hippo CMS together with any
         addons using maven commands and kill the running CMS using Ctrl-C.
         Assuming that the project directory is '~/cms'
         (after you have <a href='../svn/get_Hippo_CMS_source.html'>checked out the Hippo CMS source</a> to it):
        </p>
        <source>
&gt; cd ~/cms
~/cms&gt; mvn install
~/cms&gt; cd quickstart/war
~/cms/quickstart/war&gt; mvn clean jetty:run-war
        </source>
        <p>
         Maven uses the application server Jetty, which is included with Maven.
         <code>mvn install</code> does the same as <code>mvn package</code> (i.e. building the packages)
         and in addition puts all project artifacts
         (jars, wars) in your local maven repository, as required by the maven-jetty-plugin.
        </p>
        <p>
         Jetty and the Hippo CMS have now started and the CMS can be accessed via
         your web browser at <a href="http://localhost:8080/cms/">http://localhost:8080/cms/</a>,
         logging in as admin/admin.
        </p>
    <p>
      Note that in the sample application started from the command line is a quickstart version of
      the Hippo CMS suite.  If you require a production build, want to extend Hippo CMS or just
      want a clean start you should use the cms/package/war of cms/package/ear project.
    </p>
  </section>
 </body>
</document>

