<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 Hippo
  
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License"); 
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License. 
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" 
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. 
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and 
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>What is Hippo ECM?</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="What is Hippo ECM?">
      <p> Hippo ECM bundles a set of applications for managing information in large-scale
        organizational environments.</p>
      <p> Managing all information in an organization is a daunting task. Knowledge is stored in
        numerous files, emails, webpages, forms, Excel sheets, and so on, and is handled differently
        for every organization. To work with all this information, every organization employs a
        diverse set of applications that adds logic and behaviour. How to integrate those
        applications, manage the underlaying information and present the end user with a simple,
        unified environment for all their information management?</p>
      <p>Hippo ECM structures information, offers integration possibilities on both content and
        presentation level, in a simple and for users understandable way. </p>
    </section>

    <section name="History of Hippo ECM">
      <p>The first stable distribution of Hippo CMS version 6 was released in June 2004. This new
        release introduced a fresh architecture where Hippo CMS, a frontend application and the
        content repository were seperated in different server applications. This seperation of
        concerns on setup level has been one of the main drivers of the success of Hippo CMS v6.0.
        It allowed for complex integrations with external systems while keeping a strong focus on a
        standardized user interface for the end-user. The focus on standardized protocols and XML
        technologies opened up the possibilities needed for enterprise wide CMS usage. Scalability
        and load balancing functionalities have added to the stability of the platform and allowed
        it to be used in the largest, content rich environments. A familiar user interface driven by
        AJAX technologies to update only those parts of the application that needed to do so brought
        wide user acceptance. On the developer's side, the concept of deployments and custom builds
        allowed external developers to setup and use the Hippo CMS platform for a diverse set of
        applications. </p>
      <p> All of these developments combined have led to the current stable v6.04 release, rich in
        functionalities and possibilities. They have also inspired developers and customers to raise
        ideas and whishes that go far beyond what's possible today. But the architectural concept
        has proven itself, and those new ideas only intensify the feeling that we're on the right
        track. We are facing new horizons and need to take that leap to jump to the next level of
        extendibility, user experience and scalability. Together with the HippoCMS.org community,
        Hippo will be driving the development of the future version of the Hippo Content Platform,
        consisting of Hippo CMS v7, Hippo Repository v2 and Hippo Portal v1. </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
