<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2007 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Community support</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Community Support">
  
      Apart from this documentation and <a href="http://www.onehippo.com/en/support">commercial support</a>,
      support can be obtained from the Hippo community:

      <ul>
       <li><a href="../mail-lists.html">Hippo ECM mailing list</a>: if you subscribe to this
          mailing list, you can ask you questions here.
          Many other users and Hippo ECM developers will answer your questions. 
          Allow for a few hours or days to receive answers. Allthough many questions
          are answered in the mailing list, no guarantees can be given.
         <p>
          Note that it is general mailing list etiquete to ask only after you checked
          that your question was not answered before. Checking for previously answered
          questions is done in the mailing list archive, see below.
	 </p>
       </li>
       <li>
        <a href="http://lists.hippo.nl/pipermail/hipporepos-dev/">CMS mailing list archive</a>: 
            The archive of all previously asked questions and their responses. Search
            in the archive for your question. In many cases you will find the answer to your
            question within a few minutes.
       </li>

       <li>
        <a href="http://issues.hippo.nl/browse/HREPTWO">Hippo CMS issue tracker</a>:
          Read here what issues the developers of Hippo CMS have been and are currently working on.  
          Only Hippo developers and some partners can open issues in the issue tracker, but 
          anyone can contact the developers by email. They are listed as administrators of the Hippo issue
          tracker at the <a href="http://issues.hippo.nl">Hippo issue tracker homepage</a>, with their
          email adresses (see the bottom of the Login box).            
       </li>

       <li>
        <a href="http://wiki.hippo.nl/display/CMS/Hippo+CMS+Home">Hippo CMS wiki</a>: Sign up yourself and join 
           the community effort to create more documentation. You can also just read the community 
           created documentation. This is possible without signing up. You will find documenation 
           written by other users and by Hippo developers.
       </li>

      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>