<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
____________________________________________________________________________________________

-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Information Architects Guide</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Information Architects Guide">
      <span class="shortdesc">Guide for Hippo CMS users to perform the role of Information Architect.</span>

<p>
  In Hippo CMS, contributors write documents that are of a certain document type.
  The document type specifies what kind of information the document should provide.
  Documents that contain the same kind of information are in that respect similar.
</p>

<p>
The guaranteed similarity of many different documents allows
fast development of any application that
makes use of the documents. For example, similar documents can be rendered in the
same way on a website, therefor the rendering of all similar documents can be
defined in a single template. Given a document type, a web developer can create
this template before the documents even exist.
No rendering information is required in the
documents itself, so authors do not need to know about rendering, just about
what kind of information they are supposed to provide.
</p>

<p>Other possible advantages of the guaranteed similarity of documents is
  in performing searches (faceted search) and data mining on the documents.
</p>

 <p>
  The guaranteed similarity of documents is possible by the use of document
  types. Document types have another advantage: they are a kind of
  business rules that ensure that all contributors know what information they
  are supposed to supply.
 </p>

 <p>
  Document types are composed by information architects.
  The Hippo CMS provides information
  architects with a convenient document type editor for defining document types.
 </p>

   <p>
       A set of document types that is based on
       throughout knowledge of what the company needs
       makes content management particularly advantageous to the company.
   </p>
   <p>
    The CMS can delete obsolete parts from all documents of a particular document type.
    This only requires deleting the field from the document type and
    allowing the CMS to update all content. The CMS will then check all content
    and makes it conform to the new state of the document types.
    The time this procedure takes increases with the number of document
    that needs changing, but not much, almost linearly.
    There is some additional increase with the total number of documents (which have
    to be checked).
   </p>
   <p>
    If a new field is added to a document type, at updating all content, the
    CMS will add an empty field to each document of the type.
   </p>
   <p>
       Note that if meaningful documents already exist,
       a change to a document type may require handwork in each existing
       document of the type. This is the case if a new, independent
       kind of information is expected in the documents.
       Such new, independent information has to be supplied by external
       sources, generally human contributors.
   </p>


<p>
In the Hippo CMS,
the documents consist of fields. Documents of the same type may or must contain
the same fields. If you know about databases,
you can perceive a document as a record in a table and the type of the document
as the table. With more complex documents, the document would be related records
in several tables and the type of the document as the set of related tables
(all in a relational database).
</p>


<p>
CMS document types not only define which fields are allowed or mandatory.
A CMS document type may also define preset values for fields.
Furthermore, a CMS document type defines how a document of the type is presented
to an author: The Hippo CMS provides contributors with a document editor for writing
information into a document. The layout of the document being edited is
configurable and so is the behavior of the editor. This configuration is defined
in the document types.
</p>

<p>
The document types can be defined by nesting compound types. This allows reuse
of types and the easy definition of complex layouts for presenting documents to
be edited.
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <td>
      <a href="./tour.html">Hippo CMS Information Architect Tour</a>
    </td>
    <td>To get introduced to the role of CMS Information Architect, take the following tour.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>
      <a href="./howto/index.html">CMS Information Architect Howto</a>
    </td>
    <td>A collection of howto's for small tasks an information architect may want to do.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>
      <a href="./concepts/index.html">CMS Information Architect Concepts</a>
    </td>
    <td>A collection of concepts a CMS information architect may want to know.</td>
  </tr>
</table>

    </section>
  </body>
</document>
