<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2007 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Quickstart guide</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Quickstart guide">
<p>
The quickest way to get started is to obtain one of the pre-built packages.
Even when adding additional functionalities to Hippo ECM, you normally don't
need to rebuild Hippo ECM.  This because more functionality can be added by
simply adding the JARs containing the add-ons to the already packaged product,
or uploading them into the running packaged product. Therefore, there is no
need to do a rebuild from all the sources, one of the pre-built packages can
always be customized.
</p>
<p>
The quickstart packages contain all the core packaged products, but have been
pre-configured with a number of modules and settings, to give you a quick
overview of the product without having the laborious tasks to first enter
content, create users, etcetera.
</p>
<p>
Hippo ECM is a web-based application, and therefor is intended to run inside a
servlet or application container.  These containers accept pre-built
applications in the form of a WAR or EAR archive package, and provide basic
functions to Hippo ECM and management of your application.
<br/>
To get you started quickly, first determine the application container platform
you wish to use to run Hippo ECM.  Then;
</p>
<subsection name="Download">
<p>
Download either the WAR or EAR package.  For deployment in Tomcat or Jetty,
use the WAR package. The EARs need less configuration and can grow with your needs, 
but require an application container to run in.
</p>
<p>
Notice: Hippo ECM has not been released.  The following downloads
are snapshots of the current build.
</p>
  <blockquote>
      <ul>
          <li><a href="http://repository.hippocms.org/maven2/org/hippoecm/hippo-ecm-quickstart-war/2.01.00.12907/hippo-ecm-quickstart-war-2.01.00.12907.war">quickstart war package</a></li>
          <li><a href="http://repository.hippocms.org/maven2/org/hippoecm/hippo-ecm-quickstart-ear/2.01.00.12907/hippo-ecm-quickstart-ear-2.01.00.12907.ear">quickstart ear package</a></li>
      </ul>
  </blockquote>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Deploy, run and access">

<p>
Below you find how to deploy the application in Tomcat, GlassFish or other
application contains.  Once the application has been deployed and started, you
can access the Hippo CMS under the URL:
</p>

  <source>
http://localhost:8080/cms/
  </source>
<p>
The port number may change if you configured you application or servlet
container to run with a different port.  When deploy the application on a
machine other than your local machine you need to change &quot;localhost&quot;
to the correct machine name.
</p>

            <subsection name="Deploying in Tomcat 6.0">
                <ol>
                    <li>Download Tomcat 6.0 from the <a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/download-60.cgi">Apache Tomcat</a> website</li>
                    <li>Unpack the zip</li>
                    <li>Download the <a href="http://repo1.maven.org/maven/geronimo-spec/jars/geronimo-spec-jta-1.0-M1.jar">geronimo-spec-jta</a> to pache-tomcat-6.0.16\lib</li>
                    <li>Copy the WAR from the link above to apache-tomcat-6.0.16\webapps\cms.war</li>
                    <li>Start Tomcat with one of the startup scripts in apache-tomcat-6.0.16\bin</li>
                    <li>Open your browser and surf to http://localhost:8080/cms/</li>
                </ol>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Deploying in Glassfish or other application servers">
                <p>
                  Once your have obtained the sample EAR and have started and configured your application
                  server, you can proceed with deploying the EAR in the application server.  This procedure
                  depends on the application server.  Hippo ECM does not require any special application
                  dependent deployment procedure, nor does it dictate which application server environment
                  is required.  As example we provide the procedure for
                  <a href="http://glassfish.dev.java.net/">GlassFish</a>. Although the procedure
                  is similar for other application servers, it does differ, so check the
                  documentation of your application server.
                </p>
                <p>
                  Go to the administration console of your GlassFish installation, once glassfish is running
                  by accessing the following URL in your browser on the machine that runs the GlassFish
                  instance:
                </p>
<source>
http://localhost:4848/
</source>
                <p>
                  Login using the username and password of the administrator you had selected during
                  installation (default username is <code>admin</code> and default password is
                  <code>adminadmin</code>.
                </p>
                <p>
                  Select in the left pane &quot;Enterprise applications&quot;
                </p>
                <img src="images/glassfish1.gif" alt=""/>
                <p>
                  Then in the main pane select the button &quot;Deploy&quot;
                </p>
                <p>
                  When the page has loaded make sure the &quot;Packaged file to be uploaded to the
                  server&quot; is checked and use the browse button to select the build or downloaded EAR file
                  of Hippo ECM.  Then just choose &quot;Ok&quot; to perform the deployment.
                </p>
                <img src="images/glassfish2.gif" alt=""/>
                <p>
                  Once the server has finished, the application is now available on your server on the
                  configured hostname and portname, which is by default:
                </p>
<source>
http://localhost:8080/
</source>
                <p>
                  Note that the deployed location does not end with <code>/cms</code>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            
 </subsection>
 </section>

    </body>
</document>
