<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.

____________________________________________________________________________________________

-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Show referring</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Show referring">
     <span class="shortdesc">How to get a list of where the current
      document is used, i.e. which documents refer the current document?
      When are you warned about referring documents?
     </span>

   <script type="text/javascript">
    leftpx=300;
    bottompx=600;
   </script>
   <div class='group'>
    <div id='screenshot'><div>
      <img src="../../../../images/screenshots/cms_T07/editors/where_used_at_take_offline.png" alt='Screenshot of where used at take offline.'/>
    </div></div>
    <p>
     If you want to take offline a document via the
     <a href='../../contributors/concepts/review_mode.html'>publication actions menu</a>
     you are warned if that document is referred to by other published documents.
    </p>
    <p>
     In the screenshot the dialog lists where the panflute document is used in published documents.
     One of the documents referring to the panflute document is the flutes document.
     The editor Janine has selected this
     document and has just clicked the button 'Open documents in background'.
     The flutes document is opened
     as the active document behind the dialog so that it can be read. This means that the dialog
     may be about a document that is not the active one any more.
     The tab of that document is still there of course.
     The dialog text says 'This document', so remember which one it was!
    </p>
   </div>

   <p>
    Note that the flutes document as you see it actually does not refer to the panflute document.
    This is not an error. The published variant of the flutes document actually does refer to the
    panflute document. You can see in the <a href='../../contributors/concepts/folder_tabulation_panel.html'>state column</a>
    of the dialog that the flutes document has been changed after it was published.
   </p>

   <p>The organ document is not listed although the unpublished saved variant refers to the
      panflute document. Only documents with published references are listed.
   </p>
   <p>
     If you want to delete a document via the
     <a href='../../contributors/concepts/document_actions_menu.html'>document actions menu</a>
     you are also warned about referring documents. In this case about all references, not only
     published ones. You get the same list of all references from the
     <a href='../../contributors/howto/show_referring_documents.html'>show referring documents</a>
     action in the
     <a href='../../contributors/concepts/document_actions_menu.html'>document actions menu</a>.
   </p>
   <p>If a document has no referring documents, you will see the message:
   </p>
   <blockquote>This document is not being referred to by other documents.</blockquote>
   <p>Note that this message is exactly what you want if you are about to take offline or delete a document.
      It is not an error message, even if it occurs after the question:
   </p>
   <blockquote>Are you sure you want to take document xxx offline?</blockquote>

   <p>Note that you do not get a warning about referring documents if you
     <a href='take_offline_all_in_folder.html'>take offline all documents in a folder</a>.
     You are also not warned if you <a href='handle_request.html'>accept a request</a>
     for taking offline a document.
     The author who makes such requests is not automatically warned either.
   </p>

   <subsection name='Next'>
    <ul>
     <li><a href='logout.html'>Logout</a> (continue tour).</li>
     <li><a href='../tour.html'>tour</a>.</li>
     <li><a href='create_folder.html'>Create a folder</a>.</li>
     <li><a href='count_published.html'>Count published documents</a>.</li>
    </ul>
   </subsection>

   <subsection name='Alternative'>
    <ul>
     <li><a href='index.html'>Howto list.</a></li>
     <li><a href='../concepts/index.html'>Glossary.</a></li>
    </ul>
   </subsection>

  </section>
 </body>
</document>
