<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.

____________________________________________________________________________________________

-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Contributors Guide</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Contributors Guide">
      <span class="shortdesc">Guide for Hippo CMS users to perform the role of contributor.</span>

<p>
When a contributor writes a document in the Hippo CMS, the CMS ensures that that
document resembles all documents of the same document type.
Similar documents contain similar information and contributors are expected to
provide the expected information. To make this easy, documents consist of
inputfields. Unlike the inputfields in forms,
the inputfields in Hippo documents may allow quite complex editing.
</p>
<p>
  For a tour, or documentation of specific concepts and howto, see the table.
  For a more general introduction, see below the table.
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <td>
      <a href="./tour.html">Hippo CMS Contributor Tour</a>
    </td>
    <td>To get introduced to the role of CMS contributor, take the following tour.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>
      <a href="./howto/index.html">Hippo CMS Contributor Howto</a>
    </td>
    <td>A collection of howto's for small tasks a CMS contributor may want to do.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>
      <a href="./concepts/index.html">CMS Contributor Concepts</a>
    </td>
    <td>A collection of concepts a CMS contributor may want to know.</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<subsection name='General introduction for contributors'>
<p>
  Inputfields have a datatype. For example, a particular inputfield may allow only integers (round numbers) and
  we then say that the inputfield is of datatype integer.
  An inputfield of datatype <a href="howto/fill_date_field_in_document.html">date</a> allows only dates and times.
  An inputfield of datatype
  <a href="howto/fill_markuped_text_in_document.html">'rich text' (or html)</a> allows any text, which may run over several lines and
  may contain markup like headers, links, underlining, included images, tables, italic, boldfacing, etc.
  Note that such markup is not always desirable. For example, you would not want a table within
  a document title. You would not even want underlining in a document title, as this would look weird in
  a list of many document titles. So document titles are generally of datatype string.
  The datatype
  <a href="howto/fill_string_field_in_document.html">string</a> allows text but without markup,
  i.e. it has to be unformatted, it may not even run over
  several lines. Think of a simple <i>string</i> of characters.
  You may also encounter inputfields of datetype text, that are like strings, but allow several lines,
  or formatted text, that are like text, but allow simple markup: boldfacing, underlining and italics.
  You may also encounter custom datatypes, that are specific for your CMS.
</p>

<p>
 An inputfield may have buttons for editing and adding simple markup.
 Rich text (or html) inputfields have many buttons, but which ones depends on the choices made
 in the (custom) CMS you are using.
</p>

<p>The <a href="howto/learn_meaning_of_inputfield.html">meaning</a>,
   caption, datatype, buttons, size, color and position of inputfields have been chosen
   for the (custom) CMS you are using
   by <a href="../information_architects/index.html">information architects</a>.
</p>
</subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
