<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2007 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Quickstart guide</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Quickstart guide">

The quickest way to get started is to obtain one of the pre-built packages.
Even when adding additional functionalities to Hippo ECM, you normally don't
need to rebuild Hippo-ECM.  This because more functionality can be added by
simply adding the JARs containing the add-ons to the already packaged product,
or uploading them into the running packaged product.  There is therefor no
need to rebuild from all the sources, one of the two pre-built package can
always be customized.

The quickstart packages are the same packages as the core packaged products
are detailed in X, but have been pre-configured with a number of modules and
settings, such to give you a quick overview of the product, without having to
laborious tasks to first enter content, etcetera.

Hippo-ECM is a web-based application, and therefor is intended to run inside a servlet or application container.  These containers accept pre-built applications in the form of a WAR or EAR archive package, and provide basic functions to Hippo-ECM and management of your application.
To get you quickly started, first determin the platform you which to use to run Hippo ECM.  Then;

<subsection name="Download">

Download either the WAR or EAR package.  For deployment in Tomcat or Jetty,
use the WAR package. The EARs less configuration and can grow with your needs
(see discussion in X), but require an application container to run in.

Notice: note that Hippo ECM has not been released.  The following downloads
are snapshots of the current build.

  <blockquote>
      <ul>
          <li><a href="http://repository.hippocms.org/maven2/org/hippoecm/hippo-ecm-package-war/2.01.00-SNAPSHOT/hippo-ecm-package-war-2.01.00-20080610.193944-4.war">quickstart war package</a></li>
          <li><a href="http://repository.hippocms.org/maven2/org/hippoecm/hippo-ecm-package-ear/2.01.00-SNAPSHOT/hippo-ecm-package-ear-2.01.00-20080610.193944-4.ear">quickstart ear package</a></li>
      </ul>
  </blockquote>

</subsection>
<subsection name="Deploy the application in the container">
Now follow the guidelines for the platform you are using:

<ul>
  <li><a href="quickstart-tomcat.html">Deploy WAR in Tomcat</a></li>
  <li><a href="quickstart-jetty.html">Deploy WAR in Jetty</a></li>
  <li><a href="run-hippo-ecm/deploying-the-wars.html">Deploy EAR or WAR in glassfish</a></li>
</ul>

It should be possible to deploy these downloads in other servlet or
application containers.  Select the closest resembling container above and
repoduce the steps adapted for your other container if your container is not
listed above.

</subsection>

 </section>

    </body>
</document>
