<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Concepts</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Concepts">
            <span class="shortdesc"> The concepts of the site toolkit explained. </span>

            <p> The Site Toolkit is a set of components that allows web developers to create web
                sites within a Hippo ECM environment. It is based on the concept of <i>modules</i>:
                reusable chunks of functionality from which web pages and indeed complete web sites
                can be assembled. This assembly is made possible by two additional concepts: <i>layouts</i>
                and <i>sitemap</i>. Basically, the sitemap defines for each URL in a web site, which layout
                is used, and which modules. </p>

            <subsection name="Modules">
                <p> Modules are chunks of well defined functionality, that can be displayed as part
                    of a web page. A web page can be made up of many modules, each implementing a
                    different functionality. Modules can be (re)used on different web pages. </p>

                <p> Examples of modules are a list of news articles, a search form, a list of
                    related articles, and a navigational menu. </p>
                <p> Modules are implemented as a Java class, and have a view written in JSP. </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Layouts">
                <p> Layouts describe how modules are laid out on a page. Layouts are abstract
                    wireframes: they only describe placeholders for modules, they don't actually
                    define which particular modules are used. This makes layouts reusable on
                    different pages. </p>
                <p> As an example, consider a 3-column page layout such as visualized in the drawing
                    below: </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="../../images/reference/concepts/3-column-layout.png" alt="3-column layout"/>
                </p>
                <p> The layout identifies 4 placeholders or "containers": Header, LeftNav, Content,
                    and RightNav. On one page, Content could contain a module displaying a news
                    article, and RightNav a module displaying related news articles. Yet on a
                    different page, Content could contain a module displaying a list of news
                    articles published on a certain date, and RightNav a calendar module to let the
                    user select a date. </p>
                <p> Layouts consist of a configuration stored in the repository, and a JSP defining
                    the contours of the web page, and the exact locations of the containers in the
                    page. </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Sitemap">
                <p> The sitemap is the main controller in the site toolkit. The sitemap defines the
                    URL space of a web site, attaches a layout to each page, and modules the a
                    layout's containers. </p>
                <p> As an example, consider the figure below: </p>
                <p>
                    <img src="../../images/reference/concepts/sitemap.png" alt="sitemap"/>
                </p>
                <p> In the top left corner is the 3-column layout. In the bottom left corner is a
                    bunch of modules. Right in the middle of the figure is the sitemap, which
                    assigns the 3-column layout to the URL "/home", and assigns a module to each
                    container in the layout. The result is a complete web page that is displayed
                    when the URL "/home" is requested. </p>
                <p> The sitemap consists of a configuration stored in the repository. This
                    configuration is managed through a GUI. </p>
            </subsection>

        </section>

    </body>
</document>
