<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2007 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Default Hippo ECM functionality - Workflow</title>
    </properties>
<body>

<section name="Workflow functionality">

<p>
Workflow is often defined as the automation of a business process, where
documents, information or tasks are passed from one participant or state to
another for action according to a set of procedural rules.
</p>

<p>
Hippo ECM supports these business workflows, and allows workflows to be freely
defined.  This means that the workflow rules are not just customizable, but
that any workflow may be integrated as add-on program code.
</p>

<p>
Other components, or the user through a front-end application, define when a
workflow step on a documents should be performed.  The logic which defines
whether the workflow step is valid and executes the transformations defined by
the workflow for that step is executed by a plug-in in the repository.
</p>

<p>
Workflows are executed in the repository in order to obtain a separation of
concerns.  A front-end only has the interface to execute workflow steps, the
single point where the actual implementation resides can be accessed from
independent applications.  A workflow is executed in a special context,
allowing for operations to be performed a broader access scope than would be
available to the application directly.  This cleanly separates audited logic
program code (workflows) from untrusted code (front-end).
</p>

<subsection name="Workflow model">

<p>
Hippo ECM workflow is defined as a procedure to transform part of the
information in the repository into a reprocessed form.
</p>
<ol>
<li>On which information to perform the procedure is indicated by a calling
module or through the front-end application;</li>
<li>When to perform the procedure is indicated by the calling module or
through the front-end application;</li>
<li>Which procedure to perform depends on:
  <ol>
  <li>the type of information selected in 1, because workflows are defined as
  being applicable on certain types of information;</li>
  <li>the category of workflow requested, because not all workflows are available
  in all categories;</li>
  <li>the actual method inside the workflow selected by the calling module or
  front-end;</li>
  </ol></li>
</ol>

<p>
The workflow implementation uses a very open model, where no defined rules
language is imposed on how the workflow must be defined.  Instead regular
Java code may be used.  This allows for any number of extensions and
connecting with other applications or workflow systems.
</p>

<p>
When a specific workflow is available on a selected part of information, then
the workflow may expose different steps available.
</p>

<p>
A workflow is available to other modules and to the front-end, as a Java
interface with methods.  The implementation of a workflow is provided by a
Java class implementing the interface.  The individual workflow steps are
the methods of the interface that defines the workflow.
Invoking a workflow step therefore maps directly to calling the method of the
workflow Java interface.
</p>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Workflow access">

<p>
If you want to access the workflow on information in the repository, you first
need to access the JCR node representing the information in the repository.
You can then use the Hippo OCM API for the repository to obtain a reference to
the workflow.
</p>

<p>
The following source snippet is typical to directly access a workflow
</p>
<source>
Node node = ...;
// The cast in the next statement gives access to the Hippo OCM API
HippoWorkspace wsp = (HippoWorkspace) node.getSession().getWorkspace();
WorkflowManager workflowMgr = wsp.getWorkflowManager();
// The cast in the next statement also gives access to the Hippo OCM API
node = ((HippoNode)node).getCanonicalNode();
Workflow workflow = workflowMgr.getWorkflow("workflowPlugin", node);
</source>

<p>
The workflow returned is a generic interface without workflow methods.  It
needs to be cast to the workflow interface that actually implements the steps
expected.
</p>

</subsection>

<!-- TODO
<subsection name="Configuring the workflow">
  <p>
  </p>
</subsection>
-->

<subsection name="Reviewed actions workflow">
<p>
A default available add-on for the Hippo OCM repository is the reviewed
actions workflow. It is implemented by the project at hippo-ecm/addon/reviewed-action
and included in the default CMS 7 distribution project at hippo-ecm/cms
</p>
</subsection>

</section>

</body>
</document>
