<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.

____________________________________________________________________________________________

-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Show referring documents</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Show referring documents">
     <span class="shortdesc">How to get a list of where the current
       document is used, i.e. which documents refer the current document?</span>

   <script type="text/javascript">
    leftpx=300;
    bottompx=600;
   </script>
   <div class='group'>
    <div id='screenshot'><div>
      <img src="../../../../images/screenshots/cms_T07/contribs/where_used.png" alt='Screenshot of where used.'/>
    </div></div>
    <p>
     In the <a href='../concepts/document_actions_menu.html'>document actions menu</a> of a document
     you select the action 'show referring documents'. A dialog will popup with the list of all documents
     that use that document.
    </p>
    <p>
     In the screenshot the dialog lists where the panflute document is used.
     One of the documents referring to the panflute document is the flutes document.
     The author Marc has selected this
     document and has just clicked the button 'Open documents in background'. The flutes document is opened
     as the active document behind the dialog so that it can be read. This means that the dialog
     may be about a document that is not the active one any more.
     The tab of that document is still there of course.
     The dialog text says 'This document', so remember which one it was!
    </p>
   </div>

   <p>
    Note that the flutes document as you see it actually does not refer to the panflute document.
    This is not an error. The published variant of the flutes document actually does refer to the
    panflute document. You can see in the <a href='../concepts/folder_tabulation_panel.html'>state column</a>
    of the dialog that the flutes document has been changed after it was published.
   </p>
   <p>Note that multibazar2009 is listed twice. This means that both the published and the unpublished
    variant of this document refer to the panflute document.</p>
   <p>The artificial intelligence document is listed once. Its state icon shows that it is published and
      has not been changed after publication. So there is only one saved variant of this document and this
      refers to the panflute document.</p>
   <p>The organ document has two saved variants and is listed once, just like the document flutes.
    However, the organ document has the reference to the panflute document in the unpublished variant, while
    the flutes document has the reference in the published variant. You can not know that from the list.
   </p>

   <subsection name='Next'>
    <ul>
     <li><a href='request_take_offline.html'>Request take offline</a>.</li>
     <li><a href='schedule_publication.html'>Schedule publication</a>.</li>
     <!--  <li><a href='./goto_document_tab.html'>Open another document</a>.</li> -->
     <li><a href='./goto_folder.html'>goto another folder (list its contents)</a>.</li>
    </ul>
   </subsection>

   <subsection name='Alternative'>
    <ul>
     <li><a href='index.html'>Howto list.</a></li>
     <li><a href='../concepts/index.html'>Glossary.</a></li>
    </ul>
   </subsection>

  </section>
 </body>
</document>
