<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2007 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Repository Plugins</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
      <section name="Repository Plugins">
<p>
The repository can be extended with additional functionality in a number of
explicit ways.  It allows the addition of:
</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="../../../run-hippo-ecm/repository-bootstrap.html">Default content,
pre-defining a namespace, and node-types</a>;</li>
<li><a href="workflow.html">New types of workflows</a>;</li>
<li>Mirroring of external data in the repository (not yet available as API).</li>
</ul>

<p>
These repository plugins are add-ons for Hippo ECM and can be built without
having the source available of the Hippo ECM.  Building the add-on should
result in a self-contained JAR file which is placed in the classpath of the
repository.  If you have a running repository, you have the option of
uploading the plugin in a special location in the repository which is also
interpreted to be part of the classpath.
</p>

<p>
However in many cases you want to package your add-on along with a clean
repository such it can be deployed as is and can run out of the box.  If your
repository is packages as an EAR (possibly along with an CMS) then just add
the JAR containing your plugin to the EAR:
</p>

<source>
jar -uf hippo-ecm-package-ear-2.01.00.ear your-plugin.jar
</source>

<p>
If you build your repository or combination of repository with CMS, then add
the plugin JAR to repackage the WAR and add the plugin to the
<code>WEB-INF/lib</code> directory.
</p>

<blockquote>
Plugins for the repository are developed <em>independently</em> from the repository.
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
A plugin should be packaged as a JAR and can be added to the repository.
</blockquote>

      </section>
    </body>
</document>
