<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
        "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
        "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
    Copyright 2009-2013 Hippo B.V. (http://www.onehippo.com)
    
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
    BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Sitemap Index</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Sitemap Index">
            <subsection name="Resolving Sitemap Items">
                <p>
                    This module resolves a sitemap index file, which contains the locations of all the sitemaps of the site.
                    A sitemap can contain up to 50.000 (unique) sitemap items. More items will result in multiple sitemaps.
                    To provide Google all the sitemaps, a sitemap index file will be created. A sitemap index file
                    is an overview of all the sitemaps that are relevant to the site, i.e. it simply indicates the
                    locations of the multiple sitemaps. Again, it acts according the
                    <a href="http://support.google.com/webmasters/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;answer=71453">specifications</a>
                    provided by Google.  See also <a href="hstsitemapcrawler.html">HST Sitemap Crawler</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Configuration">
                <p>
                    In the console under <i>hst:hst/hst:configurations/hst:default/hst:components</i> exists a component
                    called <i>forge-sitemap-index-feed</i>. This component renders the sitemap index file based
                    on parameters, which are used in the component's class <i>SitemapIndexFeed</i>. These
                    parameters can be set in the sitemapitem <i>sitemapindex.xml</i>, which can be found under
                    <i>hst:hst/hst:configurations/[YOURDOMAIN]/hst:sitemap</i>.
                    Here can the configurations and/or parameters be set. Only the parameter <i>sitemap-location-foldername</i>
                    is required. The other parameters are optional, i.e. when these parameters are not filled, then they
                    will be considered as not existing.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The parameter <i>sitemap-location-foldername</i> is the location where the sitemap files will be
                    stored.
                </p>
                <h4>Parameters</h4>
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Parameter</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>sitemap-location-foldername</td>
                            <td>The location of the sitemap folder, where the sitemap files are stored. These files
                                will be used while generating the sitemap index file.</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>assets-url-prefix</td>
                            <td>For some systems the sitemap index files are stored in the repository asset folder.
                                These systems might use url rewriting. With this parameter a prefix can be configured,
                                which is placed in front of the asset url.</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>additional-sitemap-file-url</td>
                            <td>Provide additional urls which must be added to the sitemap index</td>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Admire the result">
                <p>
                    Start your CMS and site.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Open your site in your browser, and check out your sitemap index! <br/>
                    (http://[YOURDOMAIN]/site/preview/sitemapindex.xml)
                </p>
                <p>
                    Your browser may not display the sitemap index as XML. View the page source to see
                    the sitemap index XML.
                </p>
            </subsection>


        </section>
    </body>
</document>
