<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
  <!--
      Copyright 2007 Hippo

      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
      BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
  -->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Usage tour: Managing users and groups</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Managing users and groups">
      <p>
      The HippoECM security model is build around 4 concepts, users, groups, roles and domains. 
      Users with administrative rights can switch to the management perspective 
      to do CRUD operations on these entities. 
        <ul>
          <li>User: representation of an end-user that can log in to the CMS. Users are member(s) of 0-n groups</li>
          <li>Group: logical categorization of users. Groups have 0-n users as members.</li>
          <li>Role: collection of permissions read, write and remove. Either can be true or false.</li>
          <li>Domain: collection of 'Auth roles' and 'Domain rules'.
            <ul>
              <li>
                Auth role: Maps a role to 0-n groups and/or users 
              </li>
              <li>
                Domain rules: todo
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <subsection name="Creating a new user">
        <p>
        Click on the 'New user' button (listing 1) in the left pane of the management perspective. A 
        text input field will appear where you can type the new user's username (listing 2). 
        Press enter to create the new user instance and load the edit user form.<br/>
        The new user will appear in the users list (left pane) with an asterisk marking it 
        as new (listing 3). 
        </p>
        <table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%">
          <tr>
            <td style="padding-right: 15px;">
              <img src="../../images/tour/newuser1.png"/>
              <br/>
              <em style="width:230px;display:block;">Click on the 'New user' button to add a user</em>
            </td>
            <td style="padding-right: 15px;">
              <img src="../../images/tour/newuser2.png"/>
              <br/>
              <em style="width:230px;display:block;">Type in the new username and press enter to confirm</em>
            </td>
            <td style="padding-right: 15px;">
              <img src="../../images/tour/newuser3.png"/>
              <br/>
              <em style="width:230px;display:block;">The new user will appear in the list, marked with an asterisk</em>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          The new user is automatically selected which will load the edit-user-form in the
          middle pane. Above this form two buttons will appear, "ok" and "cancel".
          Pressing "ok" on a *new* user will persist it in the repository and the asterisk will 
          disappear. Clicking "cancel" on a *new* user will remove it completly. 
          <br/>
          Clicking "ok" or "cancel" on an existing user will either save all pending changes, 
          or simply unload the edit-form again.
          <br/>
          Only after a user has been persisted for the first time, you will be able to configure
          it as a member of one or more groups. You can do this by dragging a group from 
          the groups list (left pane) into the list beneath the users form.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Creating a new group">
        <p>
          Click on the 'New group' button (listing 4) in the left pane of the management perspective. A 
          text input field will appear where you can type the new group's name (listing 5). 
          Press enter to create the new group instance and load the edit group form.<br/>
          The new group will appear in the groups list (left pane) with an asterisk marking it 
          as new (listing 3). 
        </p>
        <table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%">
          <tr>
            <td style="padding-right: 15px;">
              <img src="../../images/tour/newgroup1.png"/>
              <br/>
              <em style="width:230px;display:block;">Click on the 'New group' button to add a group</em>
            </td>
            <td style="padding-right: 15px;">
              <img src="../../images/tour/newgroup2.png"/>
              <br/>
              <em style="width:230px;display:block;">Type in the new group name and press enter to confirm</em>
            </td>
            <td style="padding-right: 15px;">
              <img src="../../images/tour/newgroup3.png"/>
              <br/>
              <em style="width:230px;display:block;">The new group will appear in the list, marked with an asterisk</em>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          The new group is automatically selected which will load the edit-group-form in the 
          middle pane. Above this form two buttons will appear, "ok" and "cancel".
          Pressing "ok" on a *new* group will persist it in the repository and the asterisk will 
          disappear. Clicking "cancel" on a *new* group will remove it completly. 
          <br/>
          Clicking "ok" or "cancel" on an existing group will either save all pending changes, 
          or simply unload the edit-form again.
          <br/>
          Only after a group has been persisted for the first time, you will be able to configure
          it's user-members. You can do this by dragging a user from 
          the users list (left pane) into the list beneath the edit-group-form.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <p align="center">
        <a href="creating_a_document_type_and_template.html">&lt;- Previous: Creating a document type and template</a>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;<a href="workflow.html">Next: Workflow -></a>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>