<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
  "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
  "http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<!--
  Copyright 2008 Hippo

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the  "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.

____________________________________________________________________________________________

-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Compound type</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Compound type">
     <span class="shortdesc">What is a compound type</span>

    <img src="../../../../images/screenshots/cms_T07/inars/compound_templates_diagram.png" alt='compound templates diagram'/>
    <p>
      Diagram of a complex layout build up from elemental layouts.
      Such a complex layout can be defined for all documents of a particular type by
      using compound types.
    </p>

     <p>
      <a href='documenttype.html'>Document types</a> can be defined by
      nesting compound types. This allows reuse
      of types and the easy definition of complex layouts for documents.
      The documents are presented with that layout in the document editor.
     </p>
     <p>
      A compound type is a simplified variant of a document type.
      Each document type and each compound type may consist of other
      compound types and each compound type is itself a component
      of its parent compound type or a document type.
     </p>
     <p>
      Each document type and each compound type defines an elemental layout for its components.
      Java developers can define several custom elemental layouts from which information
      architects can choose in the CMS. The standard CMS supplies
      several elemental layouts to choose from, e.g.: two-column, vertical list and horizontal list.
      By nesting these compounds, complex layouts can be created. The diagram above
      shows an example of a complex layout build up from the elemental layouts.
     </p>
     <p>
      Of course, document types and compound types may also contain simple fields like
      strings. Compound types are a way to define building blocks of fields that
      can be reused in several document types or other compound types.
     </p>

   <subsection name='Next'>
    <ul>
     <li>
      If you are doing the <a href='../tour.html'>tour</a>, use the back button of your browser to continue.
      (There is no hyperlink here, because you can get here from many different pages.)
     </li>
    </ul>
   </subsection>
   <subsection name='Alternative'>
    <ul>
     <li><a href='../tour.html'>tour page.</a></li>
     <li><a href='./index.html'>Glossary.</a></li>
     <li><a href='../howto/index.html'>Howto list.</a></li>
    </ul>
   </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
